<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The case of John Wilmore truly and impartially related, or, A looking-glass for all merchants and planters that are concerned in the American plantations</title>
            <author>Wilmer, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66538</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2883</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12073</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12591695</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12591695</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63957</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66538)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63957)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 970:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The case of John Wilmore truly and impartially related, or, A looking-glass for all merchants and planters that are concerned in the American plantations</title>
                  <author>Wilmer, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 17 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Edw. Powell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: John Wilmer.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Civiter, Richard.</term>
               <term>Contract labor --  Jamaica.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63957:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63957:1"/>
            <p>THE CASE OF John Wilmore <hi>Truly</hi> and <hi>Impartially</hi> Related: OR, A <hi>Looking-Glaſs</hi> FOR ALL Merchants and Planters That are Concerned in the <hi>American Plantations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Edw. Powell at</hi> the <hi>White Swan</hi> in <hi>Little Brittain,</hi> MDCLXXXII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:63957:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:63957:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE CASE OF</hi> JOHN WILMORE Truly <hi>and</hi> Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially <hi>Related,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>SOlomon</hi> the wiſeſt of Men ſaith, <hi>there is a time for all things, a time to ſpeak and a time to keep ſilence;</hi> and if ever a time for the latter; ſurely it is <hi>now:</hi> For let a Man Act, Speak or Write never ſo much for the true Intereſt of the King and Kingdom, and the ancient Conſtitutions of the ſame, and he ſhall be ſure to be diſcanted upon and <hi>ridiculed,</hi> and the words wreſted and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from the plain and genuine Sence of them by the ſophiſtical <hi>canting Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences</hi> and falſe Reaſonings of Mr. <hi>Obſervator</hi> and his Fellows, who as is plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeen to the meaneſt thinking men, are driving on furiouſly, <hi>Jehu</hi> like for ſetting up a <hi>Popiſh</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary</hi> intereſt in the Nations, and though their <hi>bait</hi> be cryed up to be loyal Proteſtants, and for the Government as eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed; yet their <hi>Roman hooks</hi> and <hi>French Lines</hi> cannot be hid, I do expect great comments by them will be made upon the putting out of my Caſe, and how I might have ſpared my pains in troubling of the World with a large <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noramus</hi> Story, for that there is a <hi>Verdict</hi> againſt me, that ſhews what I am, with much more ſuch ſtuff. Now had my Caſe been <hi>ſingle,</hi> and I had ſuffered never ſo unjuſtly by it, though it had been my ruine, I would have been ſilent, and with patience waited the time of the <hi>Great Lord Chief Juſtice</hi> of all the earth, whoſe Commiſſion is in himſelf for ever, and who will do right, and cannot do wrong, for he is infallible, and no reſpecter of perſons. But con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering as I am made the firſt <hi>Example</hi> of this kind, and may not be the <hi>last,</hi> eſpecially if Popiſh malice ſee it for their advantage, ſeeing <hi>many thouſands</hi> of people are concerned in moſt of the conſiderable parts of this Kingdom, and <hi>Ireland,</hi> either in one Plantation or other in <hi>America,</hi> I thought it my du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for <hi>their ſakes</hi> to give the World a true and impartial <hi>State</hi> of my Caſe, that it might be a <hi>Looking-Glaſs</hi> to them, thereby to ſee what they muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, if malice will proſecute.</p>
            <p>I will not trouble you with any thing done in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> leaſt it ſhould be reflected upon as arraigning the <hi>Juſtice</hi> of the Nation, I ſhall only give you the Truth of it, as it was before it went in there, and ſomething of their witneſſes. Were my Accuſation as <hi>Tompſon</hi> and his gang have given out for being a <hi>Kidnapper</hi> or <hi>Stealer of Children,</hi> I muſt have acknowledged it
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:63957:3"/>to have been abominable, for of all theft, the ſtealing of a Child is the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, nothing being ſo dear in the world to Parents as their Children, and I bleſs God, in my whole life, I never ſent over Sea, Man, Woman, or Child, without their <hi>free conſent.</hi> The matter of Fact in truth (for which I am now troubled) is this: In March laſt was two years, I ſent ſeveral workmen, as <hi>Carpenters</hi> and others upon wages to <hi>Jamaica,</hi> we came down to take water at <hi>Billingſgate,</hi> but the Tide was not ready, I had beſides my workmen a boy bound to me by Juſtice <hi>Daſhwood</hi> of <hi>Hackney,</hi> to ſend to <hi>Jamaica,</hi> being a poor boy he had kept; I had alſo with me a boy of Mr. <hi>Alexander Hoſeas,</hi> bound to him by his friends, to go to <hi>Jamaica.</hi> We went into an houſe, to ſtay till the Tide was ready, and bought ſome Pipes, Tobacco and Brandy, to take with us in the boat, we had not been long in the houſe, but (as boys uſe to do, who cannot ſit long in a place) the two boys went out to play upon the Key or Wharf, they had not been there long, but another boy, one <hi>Richard Ceviter,</hi> as he ſaid his name was, came to them, and diſcourſing together, the ſaid <hi>Civiter</hi> underſtanding they were going to Sea, told them he would go too, whereupon the boys came and told me, there was a boy would go to Sea with them, I bid them bring him in, whereupon he came, when I ſaw him, I told him <hi>I</hi> ſuppoſed he was ſome mans <hi>Son,</hi> or <hi>Servant,</hi> therefore would not meddle with him, and bid him go and mind his Fathers or Maſters buſineſs, he replied to me, <hi>He had neither Father, Mother, nor Maſter, nor any friend</hi> he knew of, where he might have Bread; yet <hi>I</hi> was not ſatisfied, but bid him begon, <hi>I</hi> would not meddle with him, ſo he went out, and the boys alſo, and <hi>I</hi> thought I was quit of him, but the two other boys went in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my boat, and this <hi>Civiter</hi> alſo, unknown to me, went with them, when the <hi>Tide</hi> was ready, the water-men called us to go, and when we came into the boat and found there alſo <hi>Civiter,</hi> I bid him be gon out, for <hi>I</hi> would have nothing to do with him, but he prayed me for Gods ſake, and Cryed and Roared, and unleſs <hi>I</hi> would have turned him out by Head and Shoulders, he would not go; whereupon <hi>One</hi> from the Key ſide, as <hi>I</hi> ſuppoſe ſeing the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle in the Boat to get the boy out, called to me and told me, if <hi>I</hi> took the boy <hi>I</hi> ſhould do a <hi>Charitable deed,</hi> for that he had been a little before <hi>pilfering of Sugar</hi> upon the Key, and might come to the <hi>Gallows</hi> if he ſtayed here, but might make an honeſt man if he went beyond Sea; upon this, &amp; the water-mans ſaying it would be no harm to carry him to <hi>Graves-end; I</hi> was contented; but all the way as we went <hi>I</hi> uſed my beſt underſtanding in his examining that if poſſible <hi>I</hi> could find him <hi>vary</hi> from his firſt ſtory, but <hi>I</hi> ſee he ſtill held in one tale, only made this addition, that his Father and Mother were dead, and that there was much Rent owing to the Landlord, and he came and ſeiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Goods for Rent, and turned him out of Doors, and he had no place to go to, ſo was forced to wander about.</p>
            <p>When I came to <hi>Graves-end,</hi> I was not ſatisfied, but had the boy before the Mayor, who examined him as I had done before; and he kept ſtill in his old Tale; for if the Mayor could have found out from him any <hi>Parents</hi> or place of aboad, he would undoubtedly, as the Law directs, have given him Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and ſent him back with his <hi>Paſs,</hi> but ſeeing he could find no Parents nor place to ſend him to; he asked him then, what he would do, he ſaid <hi>he would go to Sea,</hi> and ſaid if this Gentleman (meaning me) would not take him he would go with any that would, and if he could not go in this Ship, he
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:63957:3"/>would go in ſome other; the Mayor ſeeing the caſe ſo plain, that the boy was in diſtreſs; then asked if I was willing to take him, I told him I would, hop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he might make and honeſt man; the Mayor in an Indenture bound him to me, his Clark being an Attorney, drew the Indentures; the which were Signed and Sealed interchangeably, between the boy and me; the Mayor and his Clark, with the <hi>Kings Searcher</hi> being witneſſes, and the Boys Indenture being kept for the Boy in the Mayor's Hand; the Law as, <hi>I</hi> take it, putteth the Magiſtrate to ſtand in the room of Parents, to poor Children they put out, having no Parents of their own, as this Boy always from firſt to laſt denied he had any.</p>
            <p>After this was done, I ſent the Boy in our Ship the <hi>Granado</hi> to <hi>Jamaica</hi> to my Plantation, where for ought I know he is well, unleſs he be put an <hi>Appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice</hi> to a Carpenter, or Joyner, as I think ſome of our laſt Letters have hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p>Thus as brief as I can, <hi>I</hi> have given you the true matter of Fact, and all that then appeared to me, how and in what manner the Boy came to me, and how diſpoſed of; ſo <hi>I</hi> wiſhed them a good Voyage; and all my expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation and hope in this boy, was that God might make him an honeſt man, and when God bleſſed him to be for himſelf, he might remember that God had raiſed him a friend here, to take that care of him, and provide for him, being then taken by me to be Fatherleſs, Motherleſs, Friendleſs, and help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, and as the boy often ſaid his condition was ſuch, or elſe I had never medled with him; for it is well known to moſt Merchants, that its no <hi>gain,</hi> but commonly and moſtly <hi>loſs,</hi> for any man to ſend over any Boys, Girls, or Women to <hi>Jamaica,</hi> and that <hi>I</hi> had very good Witneſſes to prove at this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry time, and in this Ship there were two boys bigger then <hi>Civiter,</hi> and by conſent of their friends ſent, who well <hi>cloathed</hi> them, and beſides gave Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to the Merchants to ſend them to <hi>Jamaica,</hi> to be imployed in Plantations, and I dare be bold to ſay, that to this time neither Planter nor Merchant to the ſaid <hi>Iſland</hi> will take any ſuch boy <hi>without Money,</hi> for they are at con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable charge of keeping, and are of little uſe for ſome years; and indeed were there ſafety to the Planter and the Iſland; <hi>I</hi> am ſure the fewer <hi>white</hi> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants any Planter has, the more it would be for his profit: but there ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been ſome diſturbance by the <hi>Blacks,</hi> and the Government finding it might be of dangerous conſequence, therefore made an Act for the future, every Plantation ſhould have one <hi>White</hi> ſervant, to every ten <hi>Blacks,</hi> being intended only for the <hi>ſecurity</hi> of the Iſland, and it is not the profit as I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, but an Increaſe of charges to the Planters; what profit there is, comes out of the labour of the <hi>Blacks,</hi> who have little more for their food, then the Earth produceth, and indeed that is very good, it producing ſeveral good <hi>Fruits</hi> and <hi>Roots,</hi> and having many good green Peaſe, for many Months in the year; ſometimes if the Maſter of the Plantation be <hi>good natured</hi> and kind, he will allow his <hi>Blacks</hi> ſalt Fiſh or Fleſh once a week, and with this they are for the moſt part well contented and very thankful, acknowledging they live better there then they did in their own Country from whence they came, and yet the great labour of all the Plantation is done by the <hi>Blacks,</hi> the <hi>Whites</hi> buſineſs being chiefly to overlook the <hi>Blacks,</hi> and to keep them in awe. <hi>I</hi> dare boldly ſay no <hi>White</hi> ſervant in <hi>Jamaica,</hi> works near ſo hard as many of our Husbandmen in this Country, or doth much more then half the work
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:63957:4"/>of a <hi>Black,</hi> and yet is more chargeable in keeping then five <hi>Blacks,</hi> and this argument alone is enough to ſatisfie any man, that no Planter in his wits will keep more <hi>White</hi> ſervants than the <hi>Law</hi> of the Country commands him, but leſs if he could; I have already given you the food of the <hi>Blacks,</hi> which is all their charge, only once a year ſo much <hi>Blew Linnen,</hi> as will cover their Nakedneſs, and a knit Cap of about eight pence a piece; now the Charges of every White Servant is as followeth, every year <hi>new Clad</hi> from top to toe, beſides recruits within the year, of Shoos, Stockings, and Shirts and other things, and for their dyet, not only all that the earth produces as the Blacks have, but over and above by act of the Country, as <hi>I</hi> am informed is allowed ſeven pound weight of <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Fiſh</hi> every week, which is a pound a day; now with good Fruits and Roots, and the bread of the Country, which is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good, for I heard Sir <hi>Thomas Muddiford</hi> when living here, ſay he had rather eat it then ours here, this <hi>I</hi> ſay with a pound of Fiſh or Fleſh a day, <hi>I</hi> ſuppoſe will not be accounted by any reaſonable man a ſhort <hi>Commons,</hi> and if this be not duly allowed them, the ſervants upon complaint to a Juſtice of the Peace, ſhall be immediately relieved, and the Planter ſeverely chekt. Now by all this, let every man judge whether white Servants are hardly dealt with, during their Term there, and when they come out of their times, they have a portion of ground allotted them where they may plant them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and if careful and diligent with Gods bleſſing, may live very comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably and well: <hi>I</hi> have known ſome my ſelf that have gone over in a low condition, yet now have arrived to Eſtates of above <hi>One thouſand pound Sterling, per annum,</hi> and theſe are Planters; though now the price of Sugar being very low, the Planter hath not that encouragement as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly.</p>
            <p>And now having given you an account of the care taken for the body of every white ſervant, ſhall give you ſome account of what proviſion is made for his <hi>ſoul</hi> alſo; by an Act of the Country, every Pariſh in the Iſland is to allow to their Pariſh Miniſter, 100 l. Sterling <hi>per annum,</hi> and beſides there is many <hi>good Gifts,</hi> and if there be not a good Miniſter in every Pariſh, it is not the fault of the Government, for they are willing to give good encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement for good men to come to them, I wiſh every Pariſh in <hi>England</hi> were able to allow every good Preaching Miniſter 100 <hi>l. per annum;</hi> but this is a digreſſion. Now to return to my firſt intended deſign to lay open before you, what farther Circumſtances hath come to the knowledg of me, ſince my ſending the boy away, as aforeſaid: About a year and aquarter after the boy was ſent, comes a Gentleman to me, and tells me there was one <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viter</hi> a <hi>Barber</hi> in <hi>Wapping</hi> had his Son ſent over to <hi>Jamaica,</hi> and he had heard that <hi>I</hi> ſent him, and therefore required <hi>I</hi> would make him ſatisfaction, <hi>I</hi> asked him what <hi>Civiter</hi> was? he told me he was a poor man, and he heard <hi>I</hi> was rich, therefore he expected Money from me; for that his Son was a <hi>Loſs</hi> to him he being helpful to him in his Trade, upon this <hi>I</hi> told him the matter and manner of Fact in ſending the Boy as is before recited, and that it was ſtrange he ſhould pretend to be his Father, when the Boy denyed he had <hi>Any</hi> living; Alſo <hi>I</hi> told him I had done nothing but what was fair, and ſhould be content any one ſhould do the ſame by <hi>mine,</hi> ſhould God bring them in the ſame Caſe, as the Boy perſiſted he was in, as being Fatherleſs, Mother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, friendleſs, pennileſs and helpleſs, and this believed by me: and farther,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:63957:4"/>
               <hi>I</hi> ſaid to him, if this <hi>Civiter</hi> had a Son run away from him that was any wiſe ſerviceable to him, and he had any Love for him, <hi>I</hi> wondred he did not lock out for him, long before this time; the Gentleman ſaid he would not have looked after him <hi>now,</hi> but in hopes to get a piece of <hi>Mony,</hi> for ſaith he, <hi>I</hi> have heard the Boy had been <hi>very unlucky,</hi> and run away from divers places and would never come to good here, and therefore hearing how <hi>I</hi> had diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him and the manner of the Boys going, he ſaid he was well ſatisfyed, that he was better diſpoſed then the parents could have done for him, therefore he vvould acquaint them vvith it, and meddle no more in it, ſo <hi>I</hi> heard no more of them, until about <hi>Three Months</hi> ago, and then one Mr. <hi>Grote,</hi> a Solli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citor, being Neighbour to this <hi>Civiter,</hi> and had lent him ſome Money; and <hi>Civiter</hi> being <hi>poor</hi> and not able to pay him, the ſaid <hi>Civiter</hi> told him of this buſineſs, and ſaid, <hi>if he would follow it, he might get as much Money as would pay himſelf;</hi> upon vvhich Mr. <hi>Grote</hi> came to me, bringing with him <hi>Civiter</hi> and his Wife, who I had never ſeen before to my Knowledg, and Mr. <hi>Grote</hi> charges me, <hi>how I had ſent away a Boy one</hi> Civiter <hi>about two years ago to</hi> Jamaica, <hi>which Boy was their Boy, and therefore they expected</hi> ſatisfaction ſhould be made <hi>for the ſame,</hi> whereupon I replyed, <hi>Surely the Boy I ſent, could not be theirs, for h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt dfaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affirmed to the laſt, he had neither Father or Mother, and I perceived here he had brought both;</hi> whereupon little more paſſed at this time farther, then giving them a <hi>Glaſs of Wine</hi> I being in a Tavern at Dinner; not many days after Mr. <hi>Grote</hi> came to me very civilly, and tells me, <hi>I must do ſomething in this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs about the Boy,</hi> I told him, <hi>I would do any thing that was reaſonable, but I knew no Reaſon I had to do any thing,</hi> whereupon, ſaith he, <hi>will you go before my Lord Mayor, and leave it to Him,</hi> I told him, <hi>I would very readily,</hi> then Sir, ſaith he, <hi>I ſhall not trouble you with a</hi> Summons, but pray pleaſe to <hi>Appear ſuch a day and hour;</hi> Accordingly <hi>I</hi> attended, where ſoon after I ſaw Capt. <hi>Sam. Jones,</hi> who had been Commander of the Ship, at the time when the Boy was ſent, whom they had ſummoned in; when my Lord Mayor was ready, we were called before him, there appeared againſt me that <hi>I</hi> knew again Mr. <hi>Groat</hi> and <hi>Civiters</hi> Wife they telling my Lord, how their Boy vvas loſt, and how <hi>I</hi> had taken him up, and Capt. <hi>Jones</hi> had carried him <hi>away;</hi> my Lord asked, vvhat <hi>I</hi> ſaid to it; <hi>I</hi> ſaid, my Lord, <hi>I own ſuch a Boy by name,</hi> and gave my Lord Account as to the Matter and Mannea of Fact, as before is recited, my Lord turning to them, ſaid, <hi>what would you have,</hi> they Anſwer'd, <hi>Their Boy again, I</hi> replyed, <hi>The Boy ſought me, not I him,</hi> and indeed by his pittiful Complaints, prevailed with me to take him, or elſe I ſhould not have done it, whereupon one Mr. <hi>Rainsford Waterhouſe,</hi> a Man of known Repute and Eſtate, ſaid my Lord, I <hi>wonder at the Ingratitude of theſe People, and what they would have, they ought to give Mr.</hi> Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>Thanks for doing ſo well by the boy, who is better provided for then they could do, for they are ſo Poor, that the Pariſh doth daily Expect, when they will come upon their Charges, I</hi> knew not one Word of Mr. <hi>VVaterhouſe</hi>'s being there, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til <hi>I</hi> heard him ſpeak, when he had done, ſaith my Lord, <hi>Look, you here, why do you come with Complaints when you ought to give thanks to God and Mr.</hi> Wilmer <hi>for doing ſo well by the Boy;</hi> upon which ſpeaks one Mr. <hi>Vavaſor</hi> vvho vvas all this vvhile a Spectator and no vvays concerned in it, or made acquainted with it, as <hi>I</hi> ſhall prove in due time, and that <hi>Civiters</hi> Wife had never ſeen <hi>Vavaſor</hi> in her Life before to her Knowledg, but he then ſpake and uſed many words to little purpoſe, that to me his Lordſhips patience ſeemed very great to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:63957:5"/>him ſo to talk, and concluded all with having the Boy again at my Charge, whereupon <hi>I</hi> told my Lord, <hi>they ſhould ſee</hi> I <hi>was ſo far from any Deſign of any Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage</hi> I <hi>had by the Boy, that</hi> I <hi>would be content to looſe all my Money disburſed in ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nding him out, which with</hi> Paſſage, Clothes, <hi>and other</hi> Charges was not leſs than Eight pounds, <hi>provided they would be at Charge for him back, and if he were not</hi> their Boy <hi>to give ſecurity to pay me all my Charges;</hi> all which I thought vvas rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable if he vvas their Boy, and they had any Love to him or deſire for him, and vvere able to keep him; I thought it vvas fair for me, to looſe <hi>my Money</hi> aforeſaid, and keep the Boy above <hi>Two</hi> Years, vvhen he could do little of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice: My Lord vvas of Opinion I offered <hi>very fair:</hi> nay farther I offered to leave it wholly to his Lordſhip if they would; but <hi>they refuſed,</hi> unleſs firſt <hi>I</hi> would be obliged to bring the Boy, and other Matters they would leave to my Lord, ſo that Mr. <hi>Vavaſor</hi> ſpeaking Words unbecoming him in the place, vvherein he ſtood, how <hi>I</hi> was an <hi>Ignoramus,</hi> on purpoſe to provoke me, <hi>I</hi> ſaid my Lord, <hi>I</hi> ſee this Gentleman hath ſome farther Deſign in hand, and is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to be doing, ſeeing therefore nothing of Reaſon will ſatisfie, <hi>I</hi> knowing my own innocency in the Matter, <hi>I</hi> pray my Lord, let them take their <hi>Courſe by Law,</hi> for <hi>I</hi> perceive, it is more than the <hi>Boy</hi> this Gentleman aims at; <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney</hi> at leaſt if not ſomething elſe, therefore pray my Lord, let them take their <hi>Courſe;</hi> upon my Lords ſpeaking to <hi>Civiters</hi> Wife, <hi>Good Woman, where is your Husband for to proſecute;</hi> ſhe anſwered, <hi>My Lord, My Husband is a poor man,</hi> and hath not Clothes fit to appear before your Lordſhip, or words to that ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, upon vvhich ſaith Mr. <hi>Vavaſor, My Lord, I will be bound with the Woman to proſecute,</hi> vvhereupon he vvith the Woman entred into a Recognizance of Forty pounds to proſecute me at next <hi>General Seſſions of Peace at Guildball,</hi> and my ſelf vvith Sureties vvere bound in the like Sum to Appear; all this while to give Mr. <hi>Grote</hi> his due, he vvas ſo Civil as to ſay very little, ſeeing I had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered ſo fair, <hi>That nothing,</hi> as he ſaid, <hi>in Reaſon and Conſcience could be ſaid againſt it;</hi> and now for what vvas ſaid and done at my Lord Mayors, ſeveral Good Citizens can teſtifie the truth of this Relation; nay <hi>I</hi> dare ſtand to the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of my Lord himſelf: <hi>I</hi> had almoſt forgot one thing farther, <hi>I</hi> offered the Woman, vvhen before my Lord, that if ſhe vvould write her mind to the Boy, <hi>I</hi> did engage before my Lord, it ſhould be carefully ſent to him, and if he did ſignine in his Anſwer to her, that he did deſire to come back; <hi>I</hi> would ſend for him back: and this is the ſence and ſubſtance of vvhat paſſed before my Lord, only ſome Words Mr. <hi>Vavaſor</hi> vvould have charged me with, as then to have ſaid to my diſadvantage, but my Lord corrected him, as charging me vvith a Falſhood, and thus we parted as <hi>I</hi> thought not to have heard from them any more until the Seſſions.</p>
            <p>But the next, or at moſt two days after came Mr. <hi>Grote</hi> to me and told me, <hi>He was very ſorry things w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re carried ſo high by Vavaſor,</hi> and that he ſhould <hi>thruſt himſelf into this buſineſs being altogether a Stranger to</hi> Civiter, <hi>and ſhe had never ſeen him in her Life before,</hi> and then when <hi>Civiters</hi> Wife came home her Husband vvas angry at vvhat ſhe had done, telling her, <hi>He had, and that ſhe knew well, given full Power by Letter of Attorney to Mr</hi> Grote <hi>to proſecute, or make an end, as he ſaw good, and to none elſe;</hi> which <hi>Letter of Attorney</hi> Mr. <hi>Grote</hi> ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me; where <hi>I</hi> ſaw <hi>Richard Civiter</hi> by his Mark, which mark <hi>I</hi> have forgot, but ſaith Mr. <hi>Grote, If you pleaſe to put the Buſineſs to Arbitration I am willing, I</hi> replyed, <hi>I was for my part willing alſo to leave it to any man, that he ſhould name
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:63957:5"/>that had the Reputation of an Honeſt Man;</hi> but I ſaid, <hi>If it be put to Arbitration, Civiter and his Wife ſhall with me enter into Bond to ſtand to the Award:</hi> Accordingly next day he brought up <hi>Civiter</hi> and his Wife to enter into Bonds with me: I being at dinner Mr. <hi>Grote</hi> came up and dined with me; there was alſo at Dinner One Mr. <hi>Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coner</hi> and Mr. <hi>Dodſworth</hi> with ſome others; I heard <hi>Civiter</hi> and his Wife was below, I ſent them down ſome Victuals, and ordered them a Pint of Wine, and whilſt we ſat at Dinner Mr. <hi>Grote</hi> choſe Mr. <hi>Falconer,</hi> and I choſe Mr. <hi>Dodſworth,</hi> and as ſoon as we had dined ſent for a Scrivener, who drew up Bonds of One hundred pounds penalty each to other to ſtand to the Award of the ſaid Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrators, and if they did not make an end of it, then to ſuch Um<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine they ſhould chooſe; the Arbitrators withdrew and conſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but in the mean time Mr. <hi>Vavaſor</hi> had been at <hi>Civiters</hi> houſe, but finding them not at home, hunted out after them, and found them out with me; and came into my room with a lame excuſe, and asked if I were not at his houſe to ſpeak with him; I told him no, nor knew of any houſe he had; if he had, knew not where it was, he replied he thought it had been me, for his Wife told him there had been a Gentleman on horſe back at his houſe, and ſaid his name was <hi>Wilmore,</hi> and would needs ſpeak with her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band; now Note, I had not been on horſe-back for above ſix Moneths before that time; but he thought that forged ſtory would ſeem the better, if he ſaid, I were on horſeback, becauſe he heard I was moſt at <hi>Hackney,</hi> and came to Town every morning, but I perceived his buſineſs was to ſpeak with <hi>Civiter</hi> and his wife, and thereupon he ſpake to them and asked the reaſon of their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing here, they told him what they had done, at which he ſtorm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and made a very great diſturbance in the houſe by his <hi>hector<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> upon which I bid him depart my room, and not come there with his flams to make diſturbances, I knew of no buſineſs he had; and with much ado got him out of the houſe; when gone, <hi>Civiter</hi> and his wife were very civil, and ſeemed not to like <hi>Vava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor,</hi> and that they were well enough ſatisfied with the boys being where he was, but thought it was reaſon they ſhould have Money, becauſe they was told I had ſent him without Law; but hovvever (ſaid they) vve are content to take vvhat the Gentlemen Arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors give us, about this time the Arbitrators broke off for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:63957:6"/>and appointed to meet at the ſame houſe the next day at Dinner, and then to diſcourſe and make an end if they could; by this means Mr. <hi>Vavaſor</hi> fearing his time would be loſt, gets his Aſſiſtant, one <hi>Carleton Beamont</hi> to go with him near <hi>Civiters</hi> houſe, where ſending for them, he gives them plenty of liquor, and treats them high, and tells them they were worſe then mad, if they made an end with <hi>Wilmore,</hi> for as for money he would help them to a great deal more, than ever they could expect of <hi>Wilmore</hi> by Arbitration, nay hundreds of pounds and more, as I ſhall by witneſs be able to prove, and farther ſaid <hi>Vavaſor, this Dog Wilmore, this Ignoramus Dog,</hi> if I do but rout him, I ſhall be made the <hi>Kings Attorney,</hi> this I am credibly informed he had the impudence to ſay, and I ſhall, I queſtion not, prove it when oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion offers.</p>
            <p>Theſe Fellows talking at this High Rate of ſuch Great ſums of money, the poor people dream't of nothing but Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of Gold and Silver; though as is verily believed never ſaw five pound of their own together in their lives; but being then pretty high in drink, they fell a rayling at Mr. <hi>Groat,</hi> telling him he drew them in to Seal a Bond of Arbitration, and had betrayed them, therefore they would go to their Arbitrator and order him not to make an end by any means; Mr. <hi>Groat</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſeeing their fickleneſs, and charging him of betraying them; ſaid he would meddle no more in it, and by his good will the Arbitrator ſhould make no end if he could help it.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:63957:6"/>
            <p>Next day according to appointment the Arbitrators met, and Mr. <hi>Groat</hi> comes and tells them what was done, and prays Mr. <hi>Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coner</hi> to leave the buſineſs as he found it, for he was accounted a Rogue, Raſcal, and Cheat, and therefore ſhould have a wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry life with the <hi>Civiters,</hi> being foul tongued people, and his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours therefore prayed him again to make an end; but Mr. <hi>Falconer</hi> replyed, Sir I hope you did not chooſe me for your fool, therefore I ſhall make an end of it if I can with this Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman Mr. <hi>Dodſworth,</hi> for I find him an Honeſt and Judicious man, upon this Mr <hi>Groat</hi> and I left the Arbitrators to themſelves and went into another room, where Mr. <hi>Groat</hi> told me what had paſſed down by <hi>Civiters,</hi> and by means of this <hi>Vavaſors</hi> wheedling them with ſuch great promiſes, that he ſhould have no quiet of his life, for <hi>Vavaſor</hi> did continually ply them ſo cloſe, that his Tale could not be heard with them; for (ſays he) <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſor</hi> ſpends Money upon them, and treats them at ſuch an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant Rate, That I cannot but wonder at the Meaning of it, and talks to them of ſuch great Sums of Money, he will get them, as makes the poor People almoſt mad. By this time the Arbitrators brake up, and told us, They as then could not agree, but would farther conſider of it until the Morrow, if then they could not agree, would give it up to the Umpire, which they had agreed on, which was one Mr. <hi>Atwood;</hi> And ſo They Appointed to meet at the Ship-Tavern in <hi>Bartholemew.</hi> Lane, but before they parted Mr. <hi>Dodſworth</hi> told me, though I had not Limited Him, and he ſaw no Reaſon I ſhould give a penny yet for Peace ſake, he had conſented to give Five Pounds; In regard the Charge would be as much to me, if not more if I brought the Boy back: Though He ſaw no Reaſon I ſhould do that, if the Boy went willingly, and was bound by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denture: I ſaid He was, and the other Gentleman ſaid the ſame, if I could but ſhew the Indenture, He would be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied; But, ſaith He, I have but your Word, That he was ſo Bound, and They ſay, He was not, Novv vvhich ſhall I Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve.</p>
            <p>I ſaid, Sir! as you are a Merchant, muſt needs know the cuſtom of Merchants, that when Servants for Plantations are bound; the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denture
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:63957:7"/>they ſign to, is always ſent with them to ſatisfie the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the Perſons they are ſent to, that thereby they may ſee when their time is expired, that then they may have their freedom; and for the other Indenture, the party bound takes it in his cuſtody, that by it, when his time is out he may demand his freedom, unleſs there be Parents appear, then they many times take the Indentures of the Lads, ſigned by his Maſter, to keep for him leaſt he loſe it: And Sir, the witneſſes live as far as <hi>Graves-end,</hi> and its impoſſible for me to ſend to them to have an Atteſt within the compaſs of your time, but Sir, let that proof reſt on me, and make an end with that <hi>proviſo</hi> that I prove the Indenture; Sir ſaith he, that will be intricate to draw, and the Umpier we have agreed on is an honeſt man; and you may get your Atteſt of the Indenture time enough to ſhew him, and I am ſure that will ſatisfie him; and when Mr. <hi>Dodſworth</hi> and I go to him, to give him account how we have proceeded, we will both tell him our judgments; if you prove the Indenture and the willingneſs of the boy to go, we think it no reaſon for you to give a farthing; but however, Sir, ſaith he, Mr. <hi>Dodſworth</hi> hath told you what he hath offered to give: And I will tell you what I offered to take Thirty pounds, nay Twenty five pounds to put an end to it: And I confeſs I have no other reaſon, but the <hi>People are poor,</hi> and I am not certain of the Indenture: Nay, Sir, ſaid I, <hi>If that be all, I can go, or ſend my Man twenty Times to Graveſend for leſs Money than Twenty pounds,</hi> therefore pray ye Gentlemen, both together, when you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver up your Truſt to Mr. <hi>Atwood;</hi> tell Him your Judgments, and what only differed, and by that time Mr. <hi>Atwood</hi> hath it from you: My Man ſhall bring from <hi>Graveſend</hi> an Atteſt of the Indenture, and the Boys willingneſs to go; And I ſhall confide in Mr. <hi>Atwood's</hi> Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs to put an End to this Branglement: Upon this We parted, and I ſent my Man to <hi>Graveſend</hi> to Mr. <hi>Walter Nynn</hi> to enquire of him what he could remember in this Matter, upon which after a little pauſe, ſaith he, <hi>I Remember the Thing very well, and have the Boys In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denture by me, that was ſigned by your Maſter, I will fetch it,</hi> which he did, and my Man took a Copy of it, and compared it, that ſo he might make Oath it was, <hi>A true Copy,</hi> if need be, thus far my Man having proceeded; the next thing was to the willingneſs of the BOY: Sir, Do you Remember any Paſſages or Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances as to that? Mr. <hi>Nynn</hi> Replyed, That He believed,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:63957:7"/>
               <hi>He examined him near an hour, and, That he deny'd he had either Father or Mother, or any place of abode, and That he was reſolved to go to Sea, either for your Master or any one that would have him. And therefore ſeeing the boy in Diſtreſs, and your Maſter willing to take him, I thought it my Duty, at leaſt no Crime, to provide an honest Maſter for a poor Boy, and ſo I did bind him.</hi> My man hearing Mr. <hi>Ninn</hi> expreſs himſelf thus freely, ſaw it was full to the purpoſe for which he was ſent: yet asked Mr. <hi>Nyon</hi> for Mr. <hi>Creſswell</hi> the Searcher: He ſaid he was <hi>Dead.</hi> Upon that my Man reſted, relying he had enough to ſatisfy Mr. <hi>Atwood:</hi> he comes back and gives Mr. <hi>Atwood</hi> an Account: and Mr. <hi>Dodſworth</hi> delivers him over the Power of Umpire, and ſatisfies him where Only the Let was; Mr. <hi>Folkoner</hi> only wrote to him, as I think. But whether the Woman, by <hi>Vavaoſor</hi> Inſtigation, diſturb'd him, or what elſe, I know not: He left the Buſineſs as he found it, ſaying, He was near 80 years of Age, and, he did not love to meddle with any Buſineſs: ſo the time was elapſed, and no more to be done untill the Seſſions which was near. My next work was to Enquire, what Mr. <hi>Vaveſer</hi> was? I quickly heard enough of him: Amongſt other things, I ſhall only Inſtance This, He hath been a great In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>former and an unnatural one, for, 'tis reported, He informed againſt his Father in Law, Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> a Rope-maker well known to be of an Eſtate, and an honeſt man: I think he was forc'd to pay 200 l. or a conſiderable ſumm upon his Son's Information againſt his Father, for going to Meetings. And by this time the Seſſions of Feace brings me to appear at <hi>Guild Hall,</hi> where I found Mr. <hi>Vaveſer,</hi> and as an Aſſiſtant to him, one Mr. <hi>Carleton Beaumont, Civiter</hi> and his VViſe, with ſome Others they had got, who were very bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy in preparing a BILL to preſent before the Grand Jury: VVhich done, after the Examining what VVitneſſes they then had, did upon their Serious weighing it, do me that Juſtice and Right, as to bring in the Bill <hi>Ignoramus.</hi> Upon which <hi>Vaveſor</hi> was ſo impertinent, as to ſay, They had more Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, therefore deſired the Court, the Jury might go out again: Which was granted: And upon Examining the other Witneſs, the Jury was farther confirmd in their firſt Verdict, and accordingly gave it in. Upon this <hi>Vaveſor</hi> had further Confidence to move the Court, That their VVitneſſes might be examined in Open Court: which was rejected. He was in a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great Rage, and his Aſſiſtant <hi>Beaumont</hi> was tranſported with Paſſion, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Altho an <hi>Ignoramus</hi> was brought in here, yet he would put in an <hi>Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> in the Crown-Office againſt me, and lay it in KENT, for that he would <hi>Colledg me</hi> or ſerve me as Colledg was ſerv'd, before he had done with me, and bid me prepare for it: And truly, I verily believe the man ſpake what was in his Heart, That if ſuch as he could get JURIES to their Minds, they would not only hang me up, but Thouſands more, like Ropes of Onions. And for a farther Account of this Mr. <hi>Carlton Beamont,</hi> I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer you to Mr. <hi>Elkana Settle,</hi> who among many others can give you one Prank of his, at whoſe Mercy <hi>Beamont</hi> did lye: there was a Record raſed by ſomebody, I ſuppoſe Mr. <hi>Settle</hi> may more certainly inform you: ſince my Retirement, I have not had Opportunity to make Inquiry into Particulars; But both <hi>Vaveſer</hi> and <hi>Beaumont</hi> by Common Fame are notoriouſly known. Now I thought my ſelf at reſt for ſome time, but my Enemys meant no ſuch Thing, for quickly was I ſerved with an old Obſolete Writ, that is ſcarce in a King's Reign made uſe of, called <hi>De homine Replegiando;</hi> which
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:63957:8"/>was made returnable <hi>immediate</hi> or immediately. I told Mr. <hi>Beaumont</hi> and the Clark-ſitter one under Mr. <hi>Trotman</hi> Secondary or Deputy Sheriff, at the Pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Counter, That I did not underſtand the meaning of it, but I would im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately adviſe with Councel, and accordingly would put in my Return: And I very happily met with Councell in the ſame Houſe, to whom I ſhew'd the Writ, and ſtated my Caſe: he ſaid, He would look it over, and draw up a Return: But before Councel could draw it up. I was next day ſerv'd with an <hi>Alias,</hi> returnable alſo <hi>immediate,</hi> being of the Tenor of the Former: and the next day was ſerved with a <hi>Pluries.</hi> By this time, my Councel had finiſhed the Return, which, by good Witneſs, was carried to the Poul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Counter, drawn by him in Latin: Therefore for the more Common Underſtanding thereof, I give it with the <hi>Pluries</hi> in Engliſh; for our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monalty generally as yet, do not underſtand either <hi>Latin Prayers,</hi> or Court-Hand <hi>Latin Writs.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="writ">
                        <head>The Pluries.</head>
                        <p>CHARLES the Second, by the Grace of GOD, of <hi>England, Scotland, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> King, Defender of the Faith, &amp;c. To the Sheriffs of LONDON, Greeting. Whereas WE have often Commanded you. That juſtly and without delay, you ſhould cauſe to be Replevied, the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of <hi>Richard Civiter,</hi> which <hi>John Wilmer</hi> of <hi>Jewen</hi> ſtreet. LONDON, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, hath Taken, and having Taken doth hold. as it is ſaid, unleſs he ſhould be taken by Our Special Precept, or, that of our Lord Chief Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, or for the Death of a Man, or for our Forreſts, or for any other Cauſe, whereby, according to the Cuſtom of <hi>England,</hi> he is not replevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; That We might hear no further Clamor for Defects of Juſtice: or that you ſhould ſignifie unto US, the Cauſe why our ſaid other Precepts to you directed, you would not or could not Execute; and you contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning (as We Conceive) Our ſaid Command to Replevin the ſaid <hi>Rich: Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viter,</hi> or, at leaſt, have not hitherto taken Care to ſignifie unto Us the Cauſe why you would not or could not do the ſame; to the manifeſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of Us and Our Commands, and to the great Dammage &amp; Grif of the ſaid <hi>Richard Civiter:</hi> Concerning which We are Amazed and extreamly moved; Therefore firmly injoyning. We do now Command you, That you do cauſe the ſaid <hi>Richard Civiter</hi> to be replevied, according to the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of our ſaid former Precepts, to you formerly directed, or elſe, That you yourſelves be before Us from the day of Eaſter, in three Weeks, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever We ſhall be in <hi>England,</hi> to ſhew Cauſe why Our ſaid Commands, to you ſo often directed, you have diſpiſed to execute, and have there this Writ. Witneſs Our Self at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> the 28th day of <hi>April,</hi> in the XXXIV. year of our Reign.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>Shellberry.</hi> By the Lord High Chancellor of ENGLAND.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:63957:8"/>
            <p>To the aboveſaid Writ, I ſhall ſubjoyn the Return, drawn up by my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, which is in theſe words following,</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="return">
                        <p>WE <hi>Samuel Shute</hi> Eſq; and <hi>Thomas Pilkington</hi> Eſq; Sheriffs of the City of LONDON, to Our Sovereign Lord the King, and the day and place within mentioned, do certifie That the within named <hi>John Willmer</hi> doth Aſſert and Claim the within Named <hi>Richard Civiter</hi> to be his Servant, by Contract between the ſaid <hi>John Wilmer</hi> and <hi>Richard Civiter,</hi> by Deed inden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: By which Indenture the ſaid <hi>Richard Civiter</hi> for a price did Bargain with the ſaid <hi>John Wilmer,</hi> to ſerve him the ſaid <hi>John Wilmer</hi> in his Affairs in the Iſland of JAMAICA, for a Term of years, as yet to come; and long before the coming to us of the ſaid Writ, he did of his own Accord paſs over unto the ſaid Iſland, by Reaſon whereof, we the ſaid Sheriffs, him the ſaid <hi>Richard,</hi> now in the Service of the ſaid <hi>John,</hi> in the Iſland afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, cannot Replevie or Deliver,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Signed by Council <hi>Anthony Welden.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Now that the World may ſee this Return was True and Honeſt: and the State of my Caſe: I ſhall here annex the Copy of the Indenture it ſelf, as followeth.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="indenture">
                        <p>THis Indenture made the 31 of March in the year of our Lord 1680 be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Richard Civiter</hi> of the one part, and <hi>John Wilmer</hi> of <hi>London</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant of the other part; Witneſſeth, That the ſaid <hi>Richard Civiter</hi> doth hereby promiſe, covenant and grant to and with the ſaid <hi>John Wilmer,</hi> his Executors and Aſſigns from the Day of the date hereof until his firſt and next Arival in <hi>Jamaica</hi> in parts beyond the Seas: and after for and during the Term of Nine years, to ſerve in ſuch Service and Imployment as he the ſaid <hi>John Wilmer</hi> or his Aſſigns ſhall imploy him, according to the Cuſtom of the Country: In the like kind, in Conſideration whereof the ſaid <hi>John Wilmer</hi> doth hereby covenant and grant to and with the ſaid <hi>Richard Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> to pay for his Paſſage, and to find and allow him Meat, Drink, Appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel and Lodging, with other Neceſſaries, during the ſaid Term: and to pay unto him the ſaid <hi>Richard Civiter,</hi> as by Cuſtom of the Country he ought, and in ſuch Caſe is uſed. In witneſs whereof the Parties above-mentioned to theſe Indentures have interchangeably ſet their hands and Seals, the Day and year firſt above written.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>Sealed and delivered in the preſence of</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>Walter Ninn, <hi>Mayer of Graves-End.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>Richard Creſſwell, <hi>Searcher.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>VVilliam Codd, <hi>Attorney.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Having brought you thus far, the ſaid <hi>Return</hi> being given in, as aforeſaid; my Councel aſſured me, according to the beſt of his Judgment, That I ſhould hear no more of it, if the Sheriff made that Return; But I ſaid,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:63957:9"/>VVhat if they Scruple it? He anſwered, Do you ſtand by it, for 'tis the Truth of your Caſe, and if they do make any other, upon their Perils be it; for if they make a falſe Return, what ever Dammage you ſuffer, you have good Remedy againſt the Sheriffs, when their time is expired: I being aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured of the fidelity of my Councel, did ſit down ſatisfied. But here I might lead you into a large Field, as to what paſſed between the She-<hi>Sheriffs,</hi> Mr. Secondary, <hi>Trotman,</hi> the Councel, and my ſelf; but its not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial; having come to a greater length already than I hoped it would; therefore now ſhall ſtudy Brevity. In fine, there was a Return made <hi>other</hi> than what I firſt put in, which was in the Lawyers term an <hi>Elongavit,</hi> the fence whereof is Engliſhed, as followeth.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="return">
                        <p>BEfore the Coming of this VVrit to us directed, the within named <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Civiter</hi> was elongated by the within named <hi>John Wilmer,</hi> to Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to us altogether unknown, ſo that the ſaid <hi>Richard Civiter</hi> we could not Replevine as within is given in Command.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Reſp.
<list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Sam. Shute</hi> Ar'. Vic. Com.</item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Tho. Pilkington</hi> Ar. Vic. Com.</item>
                              </list>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>I ſhall not now Enquire into the Reaſon, nor relate <hi>Why,</hi> and by whoſe Advice this was made, but I told Mr. Sheriff <hi>Shute,</hi> It was none of mine, and was not a <hi>True Return,</hi> if I ſuffered by it, I begg'd his Pardon, if I ſought my Relief where the Law would help me. Now by means of the laſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, it let in my Proſecutors to take out a <hi>Capias in Withernam</hi> (as they call it) directed to the Sheriffs of LONDON, upon which they iſſued out their VVarrant to take me into Cuſtody, which if I had been, muſt have lain un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the Return of the Boy, which at leaſt would have been ſix Months, it may be twelve.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="warrant">
                        <head>The Copy of the Warrant.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Poultryſs</hi> 
                           <q>BY Virtue of the Kings Majeſties VVrit of <hi>Capias in Withernam</hi> unto us directed, you ſhall without delay take the Body of <hi>J. Wilmer</hi> of <hi>Jewen</hi>-ſtreet. <hi>London,</hi> Merchant, in VVithernam, and deliver him into our Cuſtody, ſo that him we may ſafely keep untill we ſhall be able, according to the Cuſtom of <hi>England,</hi> to Replevy the Body of <hi>Ric. Civiter,</hi> whom the ſaid <hi>Jo. Wilmer</hi> hath taken, and having taken doth detain, according to the Tenor of the ſame VVrit: dated 11. 8. 1682.</q>
                        </p>
                        <trailer>To any of our Serjeants at Mace.</trailer>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Sam. Shute</hi> Ar. Vic'</item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Th. Pilkington</hi> Ar. Vic'</item>
                              </list>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>The day before the <hi>Capias</hi> was granted, I was by Rule of Court from the Kings-Bench-Court to attend, where I appeared, and then the Attorny Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral moved, I might plead to an Information in the Crown Office, being the ſame Mr. <hi>Carlton Beaumont</hi> threatned me with, which was then by Order of Court read, and is as followeth:</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:63957:9"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="order">
                        <p>THe Attorney General, this preſent Eaſter-Term, informs That the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant <hi>Jo. Wilmer,</hi> late of <hi>Jewen</hi>-ſtreet, <hi>London,</hi> Merchant, being a perſon covetous of Gain; not in the leaſt caring by what wayes and means he Livelihood, Gain and Profit acquireth, although to the Damage and Prejudice of others.</p>
                        <p>The Defendant the 30th day of <hi>April</hi> in the 32 year of <hi>Charles</hi> the now King, at <hi>Graves-End</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> in and upon one <hi>R. Civiter</hi> ſon of <hi>R. Civiter</hi> of <hi>Wapping</hi> Barber, an Infant within 13 years of Age a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Peace of Our Sovereign Lord the King, made an Aſſault and him the ſaid <hi>R. Civiter,</hi> beat, wounded and evilly intreated, ſo that of his Life he greatly deſpaired, and then and there the ſaid <hi>R. Civiter</hi> in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Ship, by Force and Arms, falſly, ſubtilly, unlawfully and injuriouſly conveyed and cauſed to be conveyed in that Ship into parts beyond the Seas, into a certain Iſland called <hi>Jamaica,</hi> falſly, ſubtilly, unlawfully and injuriouſly the ſaid <hi>R. Civiter</hi> tranſported and cauſed to be tranſported, with intention to detain the ſaid <hi>R. Civiter</hi> in the Iſland aforeſaid, for his profit, and other Enormities, to the Dammage of the ſaid <hi>R. Civiter,</hi> and to the wicked Example of all others in the like caſe Delinquents, and againſt the Peace of our Sovereign Lord the King, his Crown and Dignity: VVhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Attorny General craved Advice of the Court in the Premiſes, and to put the Laws in Execution againſt the ſaid <hi>J. Wilmer,</hi> to Anſwer our Sovereign Lord the King, the Premiſes, &amp;c.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Whereupon I was ordered to plead <hi>Guilty</hi> or <hi>Not Guilty,</hi> I replyed, That if by the Legal Courſe of that Court, I ought ſo to do; I was ready to do it: But withal told my Lord Chief Juſtice, I was ſorry that Great Court ſhould be troubled with ſo <hi>Trivial</hi> a Thing wherein was more of <hi>Malice</hi> than any thing elſe, for that one <hi>Carlton Beaumont</hi> one of the buſieſt in Proſecution had threatned to <hi>Colledg</hi> me before he had done with me. My Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Tip-ſtaff to take me into Cuſtody. If I did not <hi>immediately</hi> plead; Whereupon I pleaded <hi>NOT GUILTY:</hi> Upon which my Lord ordered a Tryal at Bar of that Court: And, as I told you in the Introduction, I ſhall not meddle with any thing done by that Court in my Tryal, being a <hi>Noli me Tangere;</hi> yet I hope, without Offence, to Juſtice, in defence of my ſelf I may touch upon the Material Witneſſes there produced againſt me: one, was <hi>Civiters</hi> wife, who ſwore ſeveral things againſt me: as my Diſcourſe and Demands at my Lord Mayor's; That there I demanded what Money I had disburſed in the Boy's Paſſage <hi>outwards,</hi> and likewiſe what his <hi>Re-paſſage</hi> would coſt: when as its notoriouſly known by many good Citizens, That thoſe things are notoriouſly falſe; for that my Offers were as are formerly expreſt. Another Witneſs brought againſt me was <hi>their Waterman</hi> who ſwore, He carried us down to <hi>Graves End:</hi> which is alſo notoriouſly falſe.</p>
            <p>Now, That the Waterman <hi>We</hi> produced was the <hi>Right-man</hi> that carried us, I ſhall make out by ſuch a Corroborating Circumſtance as ſhall ſatisfie all unbyaſſed perſons, tho, many will ſay, Its hard to find a Waterman after 2 years, that but once carried one by Water, or that never ſaw the man before or ſince; but take the Circumſtances, and then Judge. As we went to <hi>Graves-End,</hi> Some Diſcourſe between one another will be, to paſs away the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:63957:10"/>time; and amongſt other Diſcourſe, our Waterman told us, That year a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman (as I underſtand, had ſome time before) gave a <hi>Boat</hi> to be towed for, by ſeveral Watermen, and he that came firſt to the place appointed, ſhould have it: our Waterman ſaid, He got the Boat that year: By this Token ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of <hi>Billings-gate</hi> watermen told us his Name, and ſo we found him our, or elſe among the Thouſands it had been Impoſſible: Therefore whereas the <hi>Popiſh Scriblers</hi> have charged me with <hi>Subornation,</hi> and my Witneſſes with Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury. I doubt not by unqueſtionable Teſtimony of good Citizens, and others of Repute, to make out Both againſt ſome of their Witneſſes, with <hi>Vaveſor</hi> and <hi>Beaumont.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus have I given you, at large, the moſt material Things done by my ſelf in ſending over the Boy: and alſo the moſt remarkable Occurrences done or ſaid by others, from the beginning of the Proſecution, to the Tryal at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter.</hi> (Where, by the way, Note, I had above 20 Witneſſes of good Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, whereof one half of them (as I am Inform'd) was not ſworn, nor ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of thoſe that were, ever ſo much as heard: I had ſix Councels, judg'd as able as moſt as plead at that Bar, who did ſpeak little: the Reaſon of both I leave to indifferent and unbiaſſed men to judge, when the <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Manner</hi> of my Caſe was as before is ſtated and would have been fully prov'd) having done what I promiſed in the Beginning, I leave my ſelf to the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God and men, whether <hi>Guilty</hi> or <hi>Not Guilty</hi> of the Information: When ſome of the July confeſſed, They had many times done the ſame thing, and had not near ſo much to ſay for themſelves as I have, and yet thought it no Crime in them. But ſome may ſay, <hi>Every one</hi> is not <hi>John Will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> and, That <hi>ſame may better ſteal an Horſe, than another look over the Hedg:</hi> But (to requite Proverb with Proverb) that which is <hi>Sauce for a Gooſe to day may be for a Gander to morrow.</hi> Therefore if Judgment be of <hi>Parties</hi> and not of <hi>Cauſes,</hi> I am ſure no Peace can be in that at long Runn, when the Judge of Judges ſhall ſit on his Throne, and paſs Judgment upon all men according to what they have done here. That which I am more concern'd at than at my own <hi>Private Troubles,</hi> is to ſee the Unconcernedneſs of our <hi>Proteſtants</hi> one for another, and that there ſhould be ſuch Diviſions amongs US at this day, when the Common Enemy, the PAPISTS, unite in Councils and Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes for the Good of their whole Party. [<hi>Witneſs</hi> Thompſon <hi>about</hi> Godfrey] When as but one little <hi>Rat</hi> of their Tribe ſhall ſtare the Government in the Face, and give them the <hi>Lye,</hi> and tell them, he will ſhew them a Reaſon for it too, if you queſtion him; Rather than he ſhall want help, their Capt. <hi>General</hi> ſhall interpoſe for him: How then ſhould this teach Proteſtants more Witt and Policy; If <hi>Religion</hi> will not, I am ſure their Secular Intereſt ſhould: But ſome ſay, Wit is ne'er good till 'tis bought, I wiſh you'd have a Care, you do'nt pay too Dear for't. Therefore my Brethren and Fellow Citizens, Take care in the Choiſe of <hi>Good Sheriffs,</hi> and by Law adviſe and take Counſel to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, all you that are concern'd to look after the CHARTER of the City, which is granted to every individual Freeman, and confirm'd by Divers Acts of Parliament, and is as much their own, as my Land of Inheritance is mine, which cannot be forfeited but for Treaſon: And, I bleſs God, THAT I am free from, unleſs falſe Witneſſes prevail. And I am ſatisfied, That as the City was miraculouſly burnt by the hands of Papiſts, ſo it was miraculouſly
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:63957:10"/>built by the Hand of GOD to do ſome Miraculous Work againſt the PA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PISTS, and in no long time. And I dare be bold to ſay, If the CHARTER of the City of LONDON be not good, that no Charter of any City or Town Corporate in <hi>England</hi> is: Therefore, Take Care in Time, leſt you all Repent when 'tis too late. But 'tis time for me to have done with this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, Leſt the <hi>Obſervator</hi> ſay, Here is a Treaſonable <hi>Aſſociation</hi> (for I fear me according to his Doctrine, It may be ſuch for a man and his Wife to love one-another, or a Woman to teach her Child to read the Bible 'ere long) and if it ſhould be made out, 'twould be worſe then <hi>Kidnapping:</hi> for, I know to my Coſt what 'tis to be in the Tower, though that's Honorable, yet its dear, and I love not to pay too dear for my Honor: Yet my Love to all Proteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants in general is ſo great, That I would ſuffer much for them, rather than by Timerouſneſs ſtoop to any thing that is Baſe, or ſhould do the leaſt of them any harm. Have Charity and Love one to and for another, leſt you be beaten to it at laſt. Look up, Proteſtants, and unite to ſerve God, honor the King, and meddle not with them that are given to Changes, and ſtrive only to ſerve one another in Love for the good of the Whole; and be not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided by the Subtilty of the Devil, Jeſuites, or any baſe carnal Intereſt: and then you need not fear but you will finde [mark <hi>Heraclitus</hi> Num. 71] Cats enough in <hi>England,</hi> for all the Romiſh Rats and Mice that ſeek to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour us, for the Great JEHOVAH is for us, Therefore ſhall all our Enemys be <hi>Scattered.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Wilmer.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
